<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vision or dreame contayning the whole state of the Netherland warres as it appeared to a louer of the Netherlands lying in his bed, vpon the 7. of Nouember, betweene 3. and 4. of the clocke in the morning, wherein was represented vnto him a goodly country, and therein a fayre comely horse well brideled and sadled, whereat being much amazed, he sayde, behold the horse, but where is the rider? ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18445.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2477</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2477)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 578:06, 1075:06, 2012:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vision or dreame contayning the whole state of the Netherland warres as it appeared to a louer of the Netherlands lying in his bed, vpon the 7. of Nouember, betweene 3. and 4. of the clocke in the morning, wherein was represented vnto him a goodly country, and therein a fayre comely horse well brideled and sadled, whereat being much amazed, he sayde, behold the horse, but where is the rider? ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30; 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By G. Purslowe and N. Okes] for Edward Marchant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC; Purslowe printed quires A-D, and Okes printed the rest.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Text in English and Dutch, the latter with caption title reading: Een visioen in den droom.</note>
                  <note>Includes: Looke out good countrimen while you haue time and tide, behold a strange dance made about the Holland bride, with caption title; text in Dutch as well, with caption title reading: Ghy patriotten kijck uut, kijck uut, siet wat een vreemden dans, om de Hollandtsche bruut.</note>
                  <note>In two parts; part 2 has separate dated title page reading: A short and faithfull narration from certaine citizens of note of the towne of Goch .. .</note>
                  <note>Includes the Dutch edition of part 2, with separate dated title page reading: Cort en waeractich verhael wt de mont van eenighe loffweerdige borgers van holGoch, .. .</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18447.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 formerly STC 11925; identified by that number on UMI microfilm, reel 578 (part 2 only).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: part 2 lacking. Bound with STC 18437.5: Newes of the netherlands.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library, the Folger Shakespeare Library, and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 578 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy, part 2 only), at reel 1075 #6 (British Library copy, part 1 only), and at reel 2012 (Bodleian Library, title page to first part and text of second part only).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:1"/>
                  <p>A SHORT And faithfull Narration from certaine Citizens of note of the Towne of Goch, concerning the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>and wicked Treaſons attempted</hi> and concluded by eighteene perſons to haue beene executed vpon the Townes of <hi>Goch, Cleef, Emmeryck,</hi> and <hi>Rees,</hi> diſcouered by Gods prouidence the laſt of Februarie. 1615.</p>
                  <p>At London Printed. 1615.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2477:2"/>
                  <head>A SHORT AND True Narration of the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and wicked Treaſons intended againſt <hi>Goch, Cleef, Emmerick</hi> and <hi>Rees.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the laſt of Februarie, (by Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; wiſe prouidence who is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of all Treacherie) came to the knowledge of the Lords Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of <hi>Goch, Emmerick</hi> and <hi>Rees,</hi> the murtherous and falſe Treaſons practiſed by eighteene perſons vpon the ſaid Cities, for to bring them vnder the obedience of <hi>Marqueſſe Spinola.</hi> To this end, they had purpoſed to breake a hole in the Towne-walls of <hi>Goch,</hi> behinde the Nunnerie, for to let in at the appointed houre in the night, the Garriſon of the ſaid <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> and in the like manner to betray the other three Cities, at the ſelfe ſame time and houre. This execrable intention being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by one <hi>Matthias Ceulenaer,</hi> (faining himſelfe to be one of the Conſpiratours for to know their ſecrets) vnto one of the ſaide Lords Gouernours, there was a meeting ordained of the ſaide Lords Gouernours in all haſt, in the Citie of <hi>Cleef,</hi> and conſulted how to attrappe theſe Traytours: whoſe finall reſolution was, that in the night, betweene eleauen and twelue of the clocke, thoſe of <hi>Cleef</hi> ſhould ſhoot off two Peeces of Ordnance, and that there-vpon the Gouernours of theſe ſundry places,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2477:3"/>ſhould apprehend all the Traytours that were diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Thus accordingly were apprehended on the ſecond day of March, in the ſaid places, theſe perſons following, <hi>Goſen Exkens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> olde Borgmaiſter of the Towne, <hi>Albert <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uyſt</hi> Counſellour, <hi>Iacob Haſenberch, Coenraet Keyſers, Peter Exkens, Lenart R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elofſoon, Dirick van Heuck<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lum, Rutger</hi> Sheriffe, Father <hi>Cornelis,</hi> and Father <hi>Henry</hi> Friars from <hi>Gaeſdonck</hi> (a Monaſterie ſituated ſome halfe an houres going from <hi>Goch</hi>) Item, <hi>Willem B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rbier, Ian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, Goert Franck, Thijs</hi> the Hatter, <hi>Iohn <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erlinck,</hi> Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hendrick Fuyſt</hi> Licentiat of <hi>Cleef,</hi> and <hi>Matthias Ceu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenaer,</hi> the diſcouerour of this Conſpiracie, who gaue himſelfe willingly into their hands for the better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his ſafety for this happy Diſcouerie. All theſe perſons were brought together at <hi>Goch;</hi> where there was found with the afore-ſaide <hi>Iacob Haſenberg</hi> a Roule, wherein he had noted all that he had obſerued and heard theſe foure or fiue yeeres, concerning the Dukes of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi> and <hi>Nuyburg,</hi> and who were addicted to the Duke of <hi>Nuyburg,</hi> and who not; and for this purpoſe frequented daily the publike Innes, that ſo hee might in due time make vſe thereof. Beſides this, there were found with him diuers Paſquils or Libels, very vilai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly made againſt the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the reformed Religion. Some of the ſaid perſons had alſo written certaine Letters to <hi>Marqueſſe Spinola,</hi> and ſent them to <hi>Bruſſel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> by <hi>Peter Exkens:</hi> and after the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe Traytours, there came a Letter from <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe Spinola,</hi> vnto the ſaid <hi>Peter Exkens,</hi> which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and intercepted by the Lord Gouernour of <hi>Goch,</hi> the contents whereof are not yet publiſhed. <hi>Peter Exkens</hi> and <hi>Iacob Haſenberg</hi> were racked, but their confeſſion is not yet reuealed. The time will tell vs, what ſhall bee further done in this matter, and we will be ready (being aduertiſed of the truth) to make the ſame further knowne vnto all thoſe that loue the truth: Thanking God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2477:3"/>that ſuch Traytours of their owne Countrie, and conſequently of their owne Mother, are diſcouered, to the opening of the eyes of Chriſtian Princes and States, that they truſt not too much to the faire inticings of the Papiſts, and their Princes: But being bound together as a bundle of arrowes, they keepe good watch, that the Wolfe breake not in any farther by his ſubtill and cruell trickes, to the ruine of Chriſtian Religion, and the euerſion of the Eſtate of the Country of <hi>Cleef;</hi> as alſo of the neighbour-places, whom this matter likewiſe concerneth, which the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs from. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="dut">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:4"/>
                  <p>Corten waerachtich verhael wt de mont van eenighe loffweerdige Borgers van Goch, vant abominabel ende <hi>boos verraet by ſeeckere achthien perſoonen</hi> geintenteert ende beſloten op de Steden Goch, Cleef, Emmerick ende Rees, door de voorſichticheyt des alder hoochſten Godts uyt ghecomen op leſten Februwarie.</p>
                  <p>Anno 1615.</p>
                  <p>TOT VTRECHT</p>
                  <p>Ghedruckt by <hi>Ian Ameliſſz.</hi> woonende onder de Laecken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnijders, int vergulde <hi>A, B, C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anno 1615.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2477:5"/>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2477:5"/>
                  <head>Cort warachtich verhael vant Abominabel ende boos verraet, op de Steden <hi>Goch, Cleef, Emmerick</hi> ende <hi>Rees.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Pden leſten Febrauwary verleden is door de wyſe voorſichticheyt des al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhoochſten Godts (die een Vyant is van alle moordadicheden) ter ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſe ghecomen vande Heeren Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneurs tot Cleef, Goch, Enmerick ende Rees, her moordadich ende valſch verraet gepracktifeert by ſeeckere achtien per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoonen op de voornoemde Steden, om die te brenghen onder de ghehoorſaemheyt vanden <hi>Marquis Spinola,</hi> daer toeſe voorghenomen hadden een gat te maetken inde Stadts Mueren van Goch achter het Bagimen Clooſter, om doer door ter beſſemder ure ende ſtont inde nacht het Garniſoe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vanden voorſeyde <hi>Marquis</hi> inne te laten, ende voorts op ſulcke wyſe te verraden d'andere drie Steden, alle te ſaemen op den voorſeyden beſtemdeu tydt ende ſtont, ende nae dat dit voorſeyde ende execrabel voornemen, door eenen <hi>Mathijs Ceule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naer,</hi> die mede van haer complice ſich veynſde, om dat by haere ſecreten ſoude weten, aen een vande voorno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emde Heeren Gouverneurs aen ghebracht was, ſoe zon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2477:6"/>de voorſeyde Gouverneurs daeromme in allerley by malcanderen outbooden tot Cleef, hebben aldaer raet ghehouden om de verraders opt behendelicxſte te at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traperen, ende in verſeeckerheyt te nemen, ende eynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ghereſolveert dat des nachts tuſſchen elf ende twaelf uren als die van Cleeftwee ſcheuten met grof Geſchut ſouden hebben gheſchooten, yeder Gouver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur in zijn reſpective Stadt alle de verraders die on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deckt waeren ſoude ghevanghen nemen, ende zijn dien volghende op den tweeden Martij gheapprehendeert inde reſpective plaetſen, dees nae benoemde perſonen, als naementlick <hi>Goſen Exkens</hi> out Burghemeeſter der voorſeyde Stadt, <hi>Aelbert-Vuyſt, Raet, Iacob Haſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berch, Coenraet Keyſers, Peter Exkens, Leenardt Roelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efſoon, Arent Roclofſoon, Dirck van Heuckelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Rutgher Abels</hi> Scheepen, <hi>Heer Cornelis, Heer Henrick</hi> beyde Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicken wt de Gaeſdonck, een Clooſter ghelegen ontrent een halve ure van Goch, <hi>Willem Berbier, Ian Abels, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert Franck, Thijs</hi> den Hoemaker, <hi>Ian Verlinck, Meeſter Heyndrick Fuyſt</hi> Licentiat van Cleef, ende <hi>Mathijs Ceu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenaer,</hi> als ondecker van deſe conſpiratie die hem ghewil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lichlickenin apprenhentie gheſtelt heeſt, tot ſekerheyt van zijn heylſame outdeckinghe, deſe alle zijn te ſamen tot Goch ghebracht, by den voornoemden <hi>Iacob Haſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berch</hi> is gevo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeckere Rolle waerinne by gheteeckent hadde alle het ghene hy ſedert vier ende vijf iaeren her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waerts wt d'een ende d'anders mont ghehoort hadde, ſoo den Hertoghe van Brandenburch als Nuyburch aengaende, ende wie de ſake vanden Hertoch van Nuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burch toe ghedaen was, wie met, daer toe meeſt alle daghe inde Herberghe ghefrequenteert, om hier mede ter gheleghener tijt zijn profijt te doen, oock zijn by den voorſeyden <hi>Haſenberch</hi> ghevonden dieverſche paſquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, ſeer vileynich op den Hertoghe van Brandenburch ende de Ghereformeerde Religie fulminerende, de voorſeyde ghevanghens hadden oock ſeeckere brieven
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2477:6"/>gheſchreven aenden <hi>Marquis Spinola</hi> ende den ſelven door <hi>Peter Exkens</hi> beſtelt op Bruyſel, is ooc (nae dat de voorſeyde verraders ghevanghen waeren) ſeeckere brief vanden <hi>Marquis Spinola</hi> aenden voorſchreven <hi>Peter Exkens</hi> gheſchreven, in handen vanden Heere Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneur van Goch ghecomen, waer van den inhout als noch niet en is int licht, als oock niet de belijdeniſſe van den voorſchreven <hi>Peter Exkens</hi> ende <hi>Iacob Haſenberch,</hi> die beyde gepijnicht zijn. Wat vorder in deſe ſaecken vallen ſal, ſal den tijt leeren, ende wy, als wy de wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erheyt ſullen ver ſtaen hebben, bereyt zijn alle waerheyt lief hebbende menſchen deelachtich te maecken, Godt danckende dat ſulcke verraders van haer eyghen Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlant, ende conſequentelick van haer eyghen Moeder in haer boos voornemen gheſteut zijn, tot openinghe der Chriſten Princen ooghen ende Herten, om de aen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock ende Sauſien, der Patps geſmden ende hare Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, met te veel te betrouwen, maer met malcanderen als ghebonden pijlen goede wachte te houden, dat nict hier ofte daer de Wolf, door zijne aengheboren wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theyt ende looſe treken erghens eenighe afſcheuringe en doe, tot ruvyne der Chriſtelucke Religie ende ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie vanden welſtant ende vrede, ſoo vant Lant van Cleef, als alled'omgh-eleghen Plaetſen, die deſe ſake mede aengaet, twelck Godt verhoede. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2477:7"/>
                  <head>Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fift his tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements giuen to Marquis <hi>Spinola.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis is Pope <hi>Pauls</hi> Commandement,</l>
                     <l>Which from his holy ſeat he ſent,</l>
                     <l>And gaue to his ſonne <hi>Spinola</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Marchants ſonne of <hi>Genua.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your God here on the earth I am,</l>
                     <l>See you adore my holy name,</l>
                     <l>And in all things performe my will</l>
                     <l>In this warre, as I truſt you will.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Firſt take the land of <hi>Gulick</hi> in,</l>
                     <l>Then to beſiege <hi>Franckfort</hi> begin,</l>
                     <l>And let the ſiege vnto't be held,</l>
                     <l>Till it conſtrayned be to yeeld.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In Winter with your Armie lie,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Heſſen,</hi> that to it is nie.</l>
                     <l>Plague <hi>Germanie</hi> with Warre, vntill</l>
                     <l>You force them to obay my will.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Make ſhew to do't in th'Emperours name,</l>
                     <l>And ſay men muſt obay the ſame.</l>
                     <l>Proceede with courage ſtout, my Sonne:</l>
                     <l>Leaue not till <hi>Germanie</hi> be wonne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Margraves</hi> Land ſee you deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>With fire and ſword kill man and boy,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2477:7"/>
Wife, mayd, and all you finde therein,</l>
                     <l>And place my ſonne <hi>Lupold</hi> therein.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let <hi>Wurtenburg</hi> the <hi>Palſgraues</hi> Land,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Baden,</hi> feele your puiſſant hand,</l>
                     <l>Bring th'heretickes into ſubiection,</l>
                     <l>By force and Spaniſh inquiſition.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Germane Monarch thou ſhalt bee,</l>
                     <l>Which for thy paines Ile giue to thee,</l>
                     <l>Take th'heretickes Townes, and lands, and all</l>
                     <l>You winne, and pay your debts with all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With neighbours houſe, wife, mayd and man,</l>
                     <l>T'your hearts deſire, doe what you can,</l>
                     <l>Or will: for all their goods and lands</l>
                     <l>I freely giue into your hands.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Theſe ten Commandements, my Sonne,</l>
                     <l>I charge you, that you ſee them done.</l>
                     <l>To your diſcretion I commit</l>
                     <l>The reſt, to doe as you thinke fit.</l>
                     <l>And ſee you breake the Vnion.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <l>OH God that art in heauen aboue,</l>
                     <l>Conuert theſe blinde-mens hearts to loue:</l>
                     <l>(That onely on their ſtrengths rely)</l>
                     <l>Or elſe deſtroy them vtterly.</l>
                     <l>And ſtrengthen ſtill the Vnion.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2477:8"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>DE</hi> SPAENSCHE GHEBOODEN, INGESTELT <hi>DOOR,</hi> Paus Paulus V.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>DEeſe ghebooden ende wet,</l>
                     <l>Van den Paus Paulus ingheſet,</l>
                     <l>Gafhy zyn' Soon, dien Spinola,</l>
                     <l>Eens coopmans Soon van Genua,</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ick ben v Godt in dit aertſch' dal,</l>
                     <l>Siet toe dat ghy vuyt recht te mael,</l>
                     <l>Met dit Crycks heyr, all myn bevell,</l>
                     <l>Gelyck ick v vertrow zeer well:</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Neemt eerſt het Landt van Gulick in,</l>
                     <l>Treckt dan naer Franckfort t' uwen gh'win,</l>
                     <l>Belegt de Statt met cloecken moet,</l>
                     <l>Lot datſe haer opgheven doet,</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>V winterleger houdt dan vry,</l>
                     <l>Int Landt van Heſſen naeſt daerby,</l>
                     <l>Ghy ſult ſo lang met crych zyn vuyt,</l>
                     <l>Dat Duytſlandt danſt nae myne fluyt,</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2477:8"/>
                     <l>Dit doet all onder deeſen ſchyn:</l>
                     <l>Men moet den Keyſer g'hoorſaem zyn,</l>
                     <l>Alſoe vaert voort met cloecken zin,</l>
                     <l>Lot dat ghy hebt t' beſte deel in,</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Des Marckgrauen, volck, goet end Landt,</l>
                     <l>Beſoeckt met gh'welt, met ſwert, met brandt,</l>
                     <l>Vermoort eall, end ſett daerin,</l>
                     <l>Myn' Soon Lupoldt, dien ick benim.</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Paltz, Baden oock, end Wurtenbergk,</l>
                     <l>Moeten daeraen, ghebruyckt vſterck,</l>
                     <l>De Ketters doet ghehoorſaem zyn,</l>
                     <l>Deur Spaenſche Inquiſitie fyn.</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Een duyts Monarcq ſult ghy dan zyn,</l>
                     <l>Met Ketters goet verſaet v fyn,</l>
                     <l>Haer Steden oock int roomſche ryck,</l>
                     <l>Wint, end betaelt v ſchulden gh'lyck.</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Met ſ'naeſten huys, wyf, knecht, end maecht,</l>
                     <l>Doet ſtoutlyck wat v hert behaecht,</l>
                     <l>Haer geldt end goet, end wat meer is,</l>
                     <l>To ecom' uwen Soldaten fris,</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Deeſe ghebooden, lieve Soon,</l>
                     <l>Beveel ick v, vuyt mynen troon,</l>
                     <l>De reſt ſtell'ick tot uwen vlyt,</l>
                     <l>Ick weet well, dat ghy nerſtigh zyt.</l>
                     <l>Breeckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2477:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>Concluſie.</head>
                     <l>O Hoocſten Gott, een heer der Herren,</l>
                     <l>Wilt dit verblinde volck bekeeren,</l>
                     <l>Die haer verlaeten op eygen macht,</l>
                     <l>Oft' verderft ſe door uwe kracht.</l>
                     <l>Sterckt de Vnie.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
